Guide to the Mary Roberts Rinehart Papers, 1831-1970 SC.1958.03
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Photographs and Artwork, 1875-circa 1948; VII.
  - Photographs and Illustrations, 1875-circa 1948; 1.
    This subseries contains black and white photographs of Mary Roberts Rinehart, other individuals, buildings, and scenes. Subjects include Dr. Stanely M. Rinehart, Stanley M. Rinehart Jr., Alan G. Rinehart, Frederick R. Rinehart, other family members, and various indentified and unidentified individuals. Many of the photographs are professional portraits of Mary Roberts Rinehart in formal attire. Portrait photographers include Harris & Ewing, Underwood & Underwood, Shelburne Studios, Otto Sarony Co., and Bachrach. Other photographs depict Mary Roberts Rinehart involved in various activities such as swimming and horseback riding. Family photographs include formal family portraits and informal photographs of the Rinehart family; many appear to have been taken out west at Eaton's Ranch and the Rinehart family's cabin there. Also in this subseries are photographs and drawings used as illustrations in Mary Roberts Rinehart's published works.
    The series begins with photographs of Mary Roberts Rinehart, followed by photographs of Mary Roberts Rinehart with other individuals, including family members. These are followed by photographs of other individuals, including family members, without Mary Roberts Rinehart. There are also several photographs of buildings, including Rinehart's houses in Glen Osborne, Pennsylvania, Washington, D.C., and Bar Harbor, Maine, as well as other images. Larger photographs and prints are housed in oversize boxes, Box 32 and Box 33.
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portrait as a young woman in white (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portraits in white (Box 28, Folder 2-3)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portrait in white, reading (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portraits: "Time of production of first play, 'The Double Life,'", 1908 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portrait: "When I went to the war - 1915" (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portrait "At Camp Sherman, in 1917" (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portrait at time of publication of The Breaking Point, circa 1921 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portraits in western attire at time of publication of The Breaking Point, circa 1921 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portraits in riding habit (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portrait indoors with bird (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portraits in sleeveless dress with ornamental sash and pearl necklace (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portrait in black dress and circlet (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portraits in white flowered dress, standing by window (Box 28, Folder 14)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portrait in white flowered dress, seated by fireplace (Box 28, Folder 15)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portrait in white dress, fur, and pearls (Box 28, Folder 16)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portraits in sleeveless black dress (Box 28, Folder 17)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portrait in black dress with jewelled pin (Box 28, Folder 18)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portrait, 1931 (Box 28, Folder 19)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portraits (Box 28, Folder 20)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart in fur (Box 28, Folder 21)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart in Eastern attire (Box 28, Folder 22)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart at typewriter (Box 28, Folder 23)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart seated at desk (Box 28, Folder 24-25)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart working at desk (Box 28, Folder 26-27)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart at desk (Box 28, Folder 28)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart in theater seat (Box 28, Folder 29)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portrait on garden steps, in hat and coat (Box 28, Folder 30)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portraits outside of house (Box 28, Folder 31)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart at bird bath (Box 28, Folder 32)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart "on the Columbia Highway", 1916 (Box 28, Folder 33)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart outside cabin in Maine, 1924 (Box 28, Folder 34)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portraits outside her Washington, D.C. house (Box 28, Folder 35)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart outside her Washington, D.C. house (Box 28, Folder 36)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart on patio [in Palm Springs, CA?] (Box 28, Folder 37)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart outdoors (Box 28, Folder 38)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart outdoors in blanket coat (Box 28, Folder 39)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart outdoors in white dress and hat, with scarf (Box 28, Folder 40)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart with "the little horse which took me on the trip with Howard Eaton", 1915 (Box 28, Folder 41)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart out West (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart at Eatons' Ranch cabin (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart on porch with bandaged dog (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart outdoors with parrot (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart feeding deer (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart fishing (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart at Eatons' Ranch and fishing - negatives (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart deep-sea fishing - photographs and negatives (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart hunting (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart with saddle horse (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart driving (Box 29, Folder 11)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart swimming (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart on cobble shore (Box 29, Folder 13)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart with boat, "in Florida after operation - stormy day" (Box 29, Folder 14)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart - trip to Mexico, 1918 (Box 29, Folder 15)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart with stunt plane (Box 29, Folder 16)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart in Hollywood with DeMille brothers and Douglas Fairbanks (Box 29, Folder 17)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart in makeup chair, circa 1925 (Box 29, Folder 18)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart on stage set (Box 29, Folder 19)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart and others, outdoors in costume (Box 29, Folder 20)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart and others, on board the Greyhound (Box 29, Folder 21)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart with unidentified individuals, May 18, 1935 (Box 29, Folder 22)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart at Tom's Island, with unidentified individuals, July 13, 1935 (Box 29, Folder 23)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart seated on steps with unidentified man (Box 29, Folder 24)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart - publicity photo with telephone girls at Bar Harbor Club, Maine, 1948 (Box 29, Folder 25)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart on tennis court with unidentified child (Box 29, Folder 26)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart on beach with unidentified man (Box 29, Folder 27)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart in car with policeman and unidentified woman (Box 29, Folder 28)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portrait with sister Olive Roberts, as children (Box 29, Folder 29)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart with Dr. Stanley M. Rinehart (Box 29, Folder 30-31)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart and Dr. Stanley M. Rinehart - trip to Middle East, 1925 (Box 29, Folder 32)
    - Rinehart family portraits - Mary Roberts Rinehart with young sons (Box 29, Folder 33)
    - Rinehart family portraits, 1909, 1915 (Box 29, Folder 34)
    - Rinehart family [in Austria?] (Box 29, Folder 35)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart and family - horsepacking expeditions out West (Box 29, Folder 36-37)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart and family - horsepacking expeditions out West (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Rinehart family with Blackfeet Indian tribe, 1916 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart in Hollywood with Alan and Ted Rinehart (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Rinehart family portrait - Mary Roberts Rinehart on steps with adult sons (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Rinehart family - Mary Roberts Rinehart with son Alan and daughter-in-law Gratia [?] (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Rinehart family - silhouettes of various family members on porch (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Rinehart family out West (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Rinehart family at Eatons' Ranch (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Rodeo - Eatons' Ranch? (Box 30, Folder 9)
    - Rodeos and Rinehart family at Eatons' Ranch - negatives (Box 30, Folder 10)
    - Rinehart family, outdoors (Box 30, Folder 11)
    - Dr. Stanley M. Rinehart portrait as a young man (Box 30, Folder 12)
    - Dr. Stanley M. Rinehart in his office in Jenkins Arcade, June 4, 1915 (Box 30, Folder 13)
    - Dr. Stanley M. Rinehart in riding attire (Box 30, Folder 14)
    - Dr. Stanley M. Rinehart outdoors in suit and hat (Box 30, Folder 15)
    - Dr. Stanley M. Rinehart fishing and boating (Box 30, Folder 16)
    - Dr. Stanley M. Rinehart seated by the water (Box 30, Folder 17)
    - Dr. Stanley M. Rinehart portrait (Box 30, Folder 18)
    - Stanley M. Rinehart Jr. at Lake Erie as a child, 1899 (Box 30, Folder 19)
    - Stanley M. Rinehart Jr. [?] as a child, in baseball uniform with teammates (Box 30, Folder 20)
    - Stanley M. Rinehart Jr. as an adult, 1933 (Box 30, Folder 21)
    - Rinehart sons as boys on pilings at the shore (Box 30, Folder 22)
    - Portrait of unidentied Rinehart son (Box 30, Folder 23)
    - Alan Rinehart as an adult - portrait and candid photographs (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Alan Rinehart in western attire (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Rinehart family wedding [Alan Rinehart and Gratia Houghton?], 1925 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Gratia Houghton Rinehart outdoors with parrot and fishing (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Gratia Houghton Rinehart with child, possibly Gratia "Topsy" Rinehart (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Rinehart family at the beach (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Frederick "Ted" Rinehart [?] as an adult, with child (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - Cornelia Gilleland Roberts (Mrs. Tom Roberts) (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - Gilleland family gravestones (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - Thomas B. Roberts portraits, 1875-1878 (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - Olive Roberts Barton (Mrs. Lowrie Barton) portrait with her daughters (Box 31, Folder 11)
    - George Doran portrait (Box 31, Folder 12)
    - General Edwin F. Glenn with horse (Box 31, Folder 13)
    - Christian R. Holmes portrait (Box 31, Folder 14)
    - Albert I and Elisabeth, King and Queen of the Belgians (Box 31, Folder 15)
    - Queen Mary of England (Box 31, Folder 16)
    - Joseph P. Tumulty autographed portrait (Box 31, Folder 17)
    - "Rex Beach and one of his specimens from Colombia" (Box 31, Folder 18)
    - Iguana on trip to Panama, 1916 (Box 31, Folder 19)
    - Unidentified man and woman at cabin at Eatons' Ranch (Box 31, Folder 20)
    - Unidentified females (Box 31, Folder 21)
    - Unidentified males (Box 31, Folder 22)
    - Buildings - Glen Osborne house (Box 31, Folder 23)
    - Buildings - cabin, possibly at Eatons' Ranch (Box 31, Folder 24)
    - Buildings - Massachusetts Avenue house, Washington, D.C., circa 1927 (Box 31, Folder 25)
    - Buildings - Washington, D.C. monuments (Box 31, Folder 26)
    - Buildings - Bar Harbor house (Box 31, Folder 27)
    - Buildings - unidentified (Box 31, Folder 28)
    - World War I - European front (Box 31, Folder 29)
    - World War I - European front and U.S.S. Pennsylvania (Box 31, Folder 30)
    - Unidentified people and places (Box 31, Folder 31)
    - Bracker, M. Leone - illustration for The Case of Jennie Brice (Box 31, Folder 32)
      Caption: "Lida was all sympathy and sweetness."
    - Christy, Howard Chandler - sketch of Mary Roberts Rinehart (Box 31, Folder 33)
    - Preston, May Wilson - illustration (Box 31, Folder 34)
    - Preston, May Wilson - illustrations (Box 31, Folder 35)
    - Weber, S.S.S. - illustration for "The Little General" (Box 31, Folder 36-38)
    - Wittmack, E.F. - "Messrs. Plumb ~ Rinehart and Rinehart Shooting Pheasants in High Silk Hats and Spats." - print (Box 31, Folder 39)
    - Images used in Improbable Fiction by Jan Cohn (Box 31, Folder 40)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portrait with bead necklace and fan (Box 32, Folder 14)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portraits in fur, 1917 (Box 32, Folder 15)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portraits in nurse's uniform (Box 32, Folder 16)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart on pier with net (Box 32, Folder 17)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart in kitchen with chef (Box 32, Folder 18)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portraits in floral dress, outside (Box 32, Folder 19)
    - Rinehart family portraits - Mary Roberts Rinehart with three sons as children, 1909 (Box 32, Folder 20-22)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart and Dr. Stanley M. Rinehart on horseback, in front of adobe building (Box 32, Folder 23)
    - Dr. Stanley M. Rinehart portrait in military uniform (Box 32, Folder 24)
    - Dr. Stanley M. Rinehart portrait (Box 32, Folder 25)
    - Rinehart family - portraits of two sons (unidentified) as boys (Box 32, Folder 26)
    - Stanley M. Rinehart, Jr. portrait in military uniform (Box 32, Folder 27)
    - Stanley M. Rinehart, Jr. portrait (Box 32, Folder 28)
    - Stanley M. Rinehart, Jr. with son George Herbert Doran Rinehart as a baby (Box 32, Folder 29)
    - Alan Rinehart portrait in U.S. Marine Corps uniform, circa 1918 (Box 32, Folder 30)
    - Albert I, King of the Belgians - autographed portrait, 1915 (Box 32, Folder 31)
    - Stills from Mary Roberts Rinehart plays (Box 32, Folder 32)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portrait at time of production of Seven Days, circa 1909-1910 (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portrait with ermine muff (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portraits in academic regalia at time of receiving honorary doctorate, circa 1923 (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portraits in fur and pearls (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portraits, circa 1948 (Box 33, Folder 7)
      Includes portrait used as frontispiece for My Story: A New Edition and Seventeen New Years.
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portrait in dark dress and pearls (Box 33, Folder 8)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portraits at desk (Box 33, Folder 9)
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart portrait in periwinkle gown - color prints of painting by Howard Chandler Christy (Box 33, Folder 10)
    - Portrait of unidentified Rinehart son as a young man (Box 33, Folder 11)
  - Artwork, 1909-1936; 2.
    The pieces in this subseries, created as illustratrions for Mary Roberts Rinehart's books and stories, are on display on the third floor of Hillman Library and in the Special Collections Reading Room.
    - Christy, Howard Chandler - illustration for The Man in the Lower Ten - watercolor, 1909
    - Christy, Howard Chandler - illustration for The Amazing Adventures of Letitia Carberry - watercolor and charcoal, 1911
    - Christy, Howard Chandler - illustration for The Amazing Adventures of Letitia Carberry - watercolor and charcoal, 1911
    - Cootes, F. Graham - illustration for The Window at the White Cat - charcoal and crayon, circa 1918
    - Fisher, Harrison - illustration for When a Man Marries, 1909
    - Flagg, James Montgomery - illustration for "Cynara" - watercolor, 1924
    - Preston, May Wilson - illustration for "That Awful Night" - watercolor, 1910
    - Preston, May Wilson - illustration for "Tish Goes to Jail" - watercolor, 1936
    - Ralph, Lester - illustration for The Circular Staircase - charcoal and crayon, circa 1908
    - Ralph, Lester - illustration for The Circular Staircase - charcoal and crayon, circa 1908
- Realia, 1918-1953; VIII.
  This series contains objects that belonged to Mary Roberts Rinehart. They include awards presented to her, mementos from her travels in Europe during World War I, and items from her desk, including those she used in her writing. Specific references to some of the items, such as those obtained during World War I travels, can be found in her writings, such as My Story and Kings, Queens and Pawns. Letters related to some of the awards she received can be found in the Correspondence series. Some of the desktop items, such as the silver inkstand with inkwell and the dial barometer, can seen in photographs in the Photographs, Drawings, and Artwork series. Notable items in the series include a long pair of scissors and a small jar of straight pins. A note with the scissors indicates that Mary Roberts Rinehart often edited her manuscripts by cutting up pages and pinning sections of text together in a different order. Evidence of this practice can be seen in some manuscripts in the Manuscripts and Notes series.
  - Academic hood, 1. (Box 34)
  - Black Sengbusch dip pen, 2.
  - Circular clear plastic paperweight with shells embedded, 3.
  - Compass in green dish with clear cover (compass is unattached), 4.
  - Dial barometer and Abercrombie & Fitch clock mounted in metal desktop stand (compass is unattached), 5.
    "TS JUVENIA FRANCE" engraved on back of clock and barometer.
  - Devotional scapular and medal sewn on to card, with silk case, 6.
    A scapular is referenced in chapter 24 of My Story by Mary Roberts Rinehart.
  - Ellery Queen's Mystery Magazine award: Bacon pistol and wooden plaque, 1951; 7.
  - Fragment of artillery shell removed from brain of soldier, wrapped in gauze, with explanatory note on envelope, 8.
    Referenced in "The Cause" in Kings, Queens and Pawns by Mary Roberts Rinehart
  - Framed letter and medal of Queen Elisabeth from the Belgian Embassy to honor Mary Roberts Rinehart's service to Belgium, December 10, 1919; 9.
  - Glass ashtray with MRR monogram, 10.
  - Medal: Monvment Commemoratif De La Bataille De La Marne, 1932; 11.
  - Medal: Exposition of Women's Arts and Industries Cancer Award, 1947; 12.
  - MWA [Mystery Writers of America] award: cermaic bust of Edgar Allen Poe, 1953; 13.
    See accompanying Edgar Allen Poe Award certificate in Personal Documents and Ephemera series.
  - Model of circular staircase, 14.
  - Narrow sterling silver Grogan Company tray engraved with MRR monogram and ornate floral design, 15.
  - Ornate round metal box with hinged lid and inlaid stones and/or colored glass, 17.
  - Pair of long scissors with explanatory note on tag and envelope, 18.
    "MRR cut ruthlessly into her yellow paper originals and typed first copies, wrote in and pinned pieces together with common pins."
  - Paperweight commemorating 100th anniversary of Joseph Horne Company, circa 1949; 19.
  - Parker fountain pen with explanatory note on envelope, 20.
    Notebook referenced on envelope is in Contracts and Business Records series.
  - Pennsylvania Ambassador citation: engraved aluminum plaque, 1945; 21.
  - Plastic cube paperweight, 22.
  - Promotional "prescription" for The Doctor, with half of capsule and box, 23.
    Prescription was originally folded inside capsule. Address on box: Stanley D. Mayer, Esq, Fantasy Magazine, 950 Heberton Ave., Pittsburgh, Pa.
  - Sengbusch inkwell - black plastic (lid is cracked) with clear glass jar inside, 24.
  - Short glass jar filled with straight pins, 25.
  - Silver figurine of horn player with inset stones or colored glass, 26.
  - Square glass inkwell with hinged sterling silver Grogan Company lid engraved with monogram and ornate floral design, 27.
    Goes with sterling silver monogrammed inkstand
  - Sterling silver cigarette box with hinged lid and wood interior, 28.
    Contains two cigarette, pencil, and explanatory note: "MRR smoked constantly as she wrote!"
  - Sterling silver Grogan Company inkstand, engraved with MRR monogram and ornate floral design, 29.
    Goes with glass inkwell with sterling silver monogrammed lid
  - Sterling silver letter opener, 30.
  - Theta Sigma Phi Achievement Award: ceramic tile (broken), 1952; 31.
  - Wooden crucifix with ivory Christ figure (broken), 32.
    A crucifix is referenced in chapter 25 of My Story by Mary Roberts Rinehart, and one is depicted on the plate opposite page 563 in My Story: A New Edition and Seventeen New Years.
  - World War I era silver plated box with Richard Caton Woodville battle scene and Rudyard Kipling quote, 33.
    Lid depicts battle scene after R. Caton Woodville, with Rudyard Kipping quote: "Who stands if freedom fall? Who dies if England live?"